<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Where the branches meet the roots</title>
<link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/blog.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<image>
<url>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/images/water-tree-root-mosaic.png</url>
<title>Where the branches meet the roots</title>
<link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/blog.html</link>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.5.57</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2025 04:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Sermon on the mountain</title>
  <dc:creator>Abby Stamm</dc:creator>
  <link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/tiberias.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This week has been difficult at work. Decisions from higher-ups have left me feeling bewildered, uncertain, and unvalued. My interpretation of the reading I chose for today reflected that.</p>
<p>My second reading this week was from John 6:1-14. This was another “Imagine yourself in the scene” activity. I imagined myself curious as I wandered after the crowd that was following Jesus. Some grasped his robes, begging for healing. Others pushed their children into his arms, seeking blessings. Some watched him warily. Many, like me, were just curious. His fame preceded him and we wanted to know if he was as great as the tales would have us believe. By the time we reached the field on the mountain - perhaps a shelf or plateau or saddle - most of the women and children had dropped away, leaving only men and a few older boys and me.</p>
<p>One of the boys carried a basket of bread and salted fish, probably diverted on his way home from the market. When Jesus declared the people (read: men) must be fed, the disciples commandeered his basket. Then they passed out the food to the men, who must have been ashamed seeing the boy lose his entire basket, because they coughed up whatever they were carrying stone soup style so in the end, everyone had food. I hoped someone would remember to return the boy’s basket with food for his family, but with his usefulness ended, the disciples apparently forgot entirely that he existed. I have felt a lot like that boy this week.</p>
<p>The activity asked, “In what way are you hungry?” I’m seeking a spiritual community that embodies the phrase “All are welcome” without shame or fear or discrimination or erasure, a community that meets people where they are and accepts them for who they are, even when the members don’t understand them. My favorite line in the Nicene Creed is “We believe in one holy catholic apostolic church”. That is the community I want, where what and how you believe don’t matter nearly as much as being part of the community and supporting and being supported by the community.</p>
<p>The image below is of a beaded flying dragon-type serpent called an amphiptere. Read more about it on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/anabiyeni/art/Beaded-pastel-amphiptere-118679559">deviantArt</a>. I wanted to pick an art piece more relevant to the story, but I’ve never made beaded bread and apparently I never posted my beaded basket online. Mountain made me think dragon, so here we are. Also, it’s spring (for a few days, until we get more snow) here in Minnesota, so pastel feels appropriate.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://images-wixmp-ed30a86b8c4ca887773594c2.wixmp.com/f/f94db2db-b96a-432a-94d7-028d717c10a1/d1ynpqf-3880c885-6170-4fb5-aa01-e7cbd0e97409.jpg/v1/fit/w_772,h_492,q_70,strp/beaded_pastel_amphiptere_by_anabiyeni_d1ynpqf-414w-2x.jpg?token=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJzdWIiOiJ1cm46YXBwOjdlMGQxODg5ODIyNjQzNzNhNWYwZDQxNWVhMGQyNmUwIiwiaXNzIjoidXJuOmFwcDo3ZTBkMTg4OTgyMjY0MzczYTVmMGQ0MTVlYTBkMjZlMCIsIm9iaiI6W1t7ImhlaWdodCI6Ijw9NDkyIiwicGF0aCI6IlwvZlwvZjk0ZGIyZGItYjk2YS00MzJhLTk0ZDctMDI4ZDcxN2MxMGExXC9kMXlucHFmLTM4ODBjODg1LTYxNzAtNGZiNS1hYTAxLWU3Y2JkMGU5NzQwOS5qcGciLCJ3aWR0aCI6Ijw9NzcyIn1dXSwiYXVkIjpbInVybjpzZXJ2aWNlOmltYWdlLm9wZXJhdGlvbnMiXX0.411mZ0KogD3UkLEMWzzM6Bt8Gr4XCxurl_6JrRdteQs" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Beaded flying serpent</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>religion</category>
  <category>catholic</category>
  <category>lent</category>
  <guid>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/tiberias.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://images-wixmp-ed30a86b8c4ca887773594c2.wixmp.com/f/f94db2db-b96a-432a-94d7-028d717c10a1/d1ynpqf-3880c885-6170-4fb5-aa01-e7cbd0e97409.jpg/v1/fit/w_772,h_492,q_70,strp/beaded_pastel_amphiptere_by_anabiyeni_d1ynpqf-414w-2x.jpg?token=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJzdWIiOiJ1cm46YXBwOjdlMGQxODg5ODIyNjQzNzNhNWYwZDQxNWVhMGQyNmUwIiwiaXNzIjoidXJuOmFwcDo3ZTBkMTg4OTgyMjY0MzczYTVmMGQ0MTVlYTBkMjZlMCIsIm9iaiI6W1t7ImhlaWdodCI6Ijw9NDkyIiwicGF0aCI6IlwvZlwvZjk0ZGIyZGItYjk2YS00MzJhLTk0ZDctMDI4ZDcxN2MxMGExXC9kMXlucHFmLTM4ODBjODg1LTYxNzAtNGZiNS1hYTAxLWU3Y2JkMGU5NzQwOS5qcGciLCJ3aWR0aCI6Ijw9NzcyIn1dXSwiYXVkIjpbInVybjpzZXJ2aWNlOmltYWdlLm9wZXJhdGlvbnMiXX0.411mZ0KogD3UkLEMWzzM6Bt8Gr4XCxurl_6JrRdteQs" medium="image"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Wedding at Cana</title>
  <dc:creator>Abby Stamm</dc:creator>
  <link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/cana.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>My favorite activity this week was the reading from John 2:1-12. This was another “Imagine yourself in the scene” activity. I imagined myself gossiping with the agogos (grandmothers) and some other women, including Mary and the mother of the groom. We watch the other guests, the newly married couple, Mary’s son with his friends. I wonder how they were invited, but feel it would be rude to ask. Maybe they are friends of the groom.</p>
<p>At some point, a nervous steward comes over to tell the mother of the groom that the wine is nearly finished. Personally, I feel there has been enough drinking today, but many of the guests, that rowdy group with Jesus for example, will not respond well if the wine runs out. Mary, the enabler, calls her son over to enlist his help. A few of us speculate how far he will travel and how much he will pay to find sufficient wine to last this crowd through the night. I had expected he would be all for dragging off a few friends to find more wine and be the heroes of the moment, so I am surprised by his rude response. Then I recall how rowdy some of his friends and wonder if he feels as I do, that there has been quite enough drinking tonight. Nonetheless, he acquiesces and leaves to do her bidding.</p>
<p>A short time later, the steward reappears with wine I am informed is high quality and we again start speculating about the cost. He won’t say where the wine had come from, but some of the other workers claim Jesus had created it, somehow magicked water into wine like witchcraft. I decide it’s probably best to stay quiet. While I don’t condemn witchcraft out of hand, I am wary of it until I know the caster’s intentions. Most of the rest of the guests are just happy there’s more wine and think nothing of it until the story starts to spread the next day and they are quick to point out, “We were there!” I stay quiet and watch.</p>
<p>The activity asked, “How do you respond to Jesus turning water into wine?” Wary. That stunt served no purpose except maybe to irk his mother, who was concerned only for her friend’s reputation. Why was he so annoyed with her anyway? Because he knew her request was selfish? I don’t understand how this is a noteworthy miracle.</p>
<p>The image below is of a wine charm I made years ago. Read more about it on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/anabiyeni/art/Beaded-grape-wine-charm-133452420">deviantArt</a>. Around that time, my mother had complained we didn’t have enough wine charms for all of the guests at our winter solstice parties, where we’d serve glog made from dad’s homemade wine, so I made several wine charms from old necklace pendants and bracelet charms. This is one of maybe a dozen that I made out of beads, and one of the few that I have kept. I recall the wine glass had been part of a gift box of Harlequin romances. I kept the glass because I liked the color; I never got around to reading the books.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://images-wixmp-ed30a86b8c4ca887773594c2.wixmp.com/f/f94db2db-b96a-432a-94d7-028d717c10a1/d27gcjo-8b41df1c-2d1c-4e8c-b01e-c5c61fab6014.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_984,q_70,strp/beaded_grape_wine_charm_by_anabiyeni_d27gcjo-375w-2x.jpg?token=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJzdWIiOiJ1cm46YXBwOjdlMGQxODg5ODIyNjQzNzNhNWYwZDQxNWVhMGQyNmUwIiwiaXNzIjoidXJuOmFwcDo3ZTBkMTg4OTgyMjY0MzczYTVmMGQ0MTVlYTBkMjZlMCIsIm9iaiI6W1t7ImhlaWdodCI6Ijw9OTg0IiwicGF0aCI6IlwvZlwvZjk0ZGIyZGItYjk2YS00MzJhLTk0ZDctMDI4ZDcxN2MxMGExXC9kMjdnY2pvLThiNDFkZjFjLTJkMWMtNGU4Yy1iMDFlLWM1YzYxZmFiNjAxNC5qcGciLCJ3aWR0aCI6Ijw9NjAwIn1dXSwiYXVkIjpbInVybjpzZXJ2aWNlOmltYWdlLm9wZXJhdGlvbnMiXX0.RWFho2UYDUZfydgNxPRfKXbKqoQIy2VrUhlp0RHXLI8" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Wine glass with wine charm of beaded grapes</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>religion</category>
  <category>catholic</category>
  <category>lent</category>
  <guid>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/cana.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://images-wixmp-ed30a86b8c4ca887773594c2.wixmp.com/f/f94db2db-b96a-432a-94d7-028d717c10a1/d27gcjo-8b41df1c-2d1c-4e8c-b01e-c5c61fab6014.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_984,q_70,strp/beaded_grape_wine_charm_by_anabiyeni_d27gcjo-375w-2x.jpg?token=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJzdWIiOiJ1cm46YXBwOjdlMGQxODg5ODIyNjQzNzNhNWYwZDQxNWVhMGQyNmUwIiwiaXNzIjoidXJuOmFwcDo3ZTBkMTg4OTgyMjY0MzczYTVmMGQ0MTVlYTBkMjZlMCIsIm9iaiI6W1t7ImhlaWdodCI6Ijw9OTg0IiwicGF0aCI6IlwvZlwvZjk0ZGIyZGItYjk2YS00MzJhLTk0ZDctMDI4ZDcxN2MxMGExXC9kMjdnY2pvLThiNDFkZjFjLTJkMWMtNGU4Yy1iMDFlLWM1YzYxZmFiNjAxNC5qcGciLCJ3aWR0aCI6Ijw9NjAwIn1dXSwiYXVkIjpbInVybjpzZXJ2aWNlOmltYWdlLm9wZXJhdGlvbnMiXX0.RWFho2UYDUZfydgNxPRfKXbKqoQIy2VrUhlp0RHXLI8" medium="image"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Boat to Capernaum</title>
  <dc:creator>Abby Stamm</dc:creator>
  <link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/capernaum.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This week also saw a reading from John 6:16-21. This was another “Imagine yourself in the scene” activity. I get motion sick very easily. I found myself reliving crossing Lake Malawi in a dhow during the rainy season. Some distance from shore, visibility dropped to zero, so the crew stopped the boat in the middle of the lake and waited for the storm to calm. I stayed by the back, drenched through, retching, and struggling just to breathe. The crew and most of my friends huddled under the tarp in the middle of the boat, but crew members were smoking there and I wanted to avoid smoke-induced nausea on top of sesickness.</p>
<p>I imagined the disciples’ crossing was much like my own journey had been. Placing myself in the scene, I was just as seasick as I’d been on Lake Malawi. As a result, if I noticed Jesus at all, I shrugged him off as a hallucination. Likely I did not notice him and was only vaguely aware of the disciples shouting. I probably assumed they were shouting at each other about the storm. They knew how sick I was; they’d likely leave me be until we reached shore.</p>
<p>The activity asked, “How do you feel when you realize you are on the shore?” I was grateful the seasickness passed quickly and I could finally focus on something other than my stomach and esophagus. Of course, by that time Jesus was long gone. Hearing the crew retell it - “How did you miss it?” they asked me - I thought they must have hallucinated. Then I went in search of beer (being generally safer to drink than water) to wash the bile out of my mouth.</p>
<p>The image below is of a Viking longboat made of Delica beads. Read more about it on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/anabiyeni/art/Beaded-Viking-Longboat-416620779">deviantArt</a>. I made it about 15 years after I spent a semester in Denmark studying Nordic culture and history.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://images-wixmp-ed30a86b8c4ca887773594c2.wixmp.com/f/f94db2db-b96a-432a-94d7-028d717c10a1/d6w1mnf-bb72cc4a-3fa3-4f0f-b48b-61dc7a273f0a.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_498,q_70,strp/beaded_viking_longboat_by_anabiyeni_d6w1mnf-375w-2x.jpg?token=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJzdWIiOiJ1cm46YXBwOjdlMGQxODg5ODIyNjQzNzNhNWYwZDQxNWVhMGQyNmUwIiwiaXNzIjoidXJuOmFwcDo3ZTBkMTg4OTgyMjY0MzczYTVmMGQ0MTVlYTBkMjZlMCIsIm9iaiI6W1t7ImhlaWdodCI6Ijw9NDk4IiwicGF0aCI6IlwvZlwvZjk0ZGIyZGItYjk2YS00MzJhLTk0ZDctMDI4ZDcxN2MxMGExXC9kNncxbW5mLWJiNzJjYzRhLTNmYTMtNGYwZi1iNDhiLTYxZGM3YTI3M2YwYS5qcGciLCJ3aWR0aCI6Ijw9NjAwIn1dXSwiYXVkIjpbInVybjpzZXJ2aWNlOmltYWdlLm9wZXJhdGlvbnMiXX0.5Mf-X2W32ArKdnjsxHWOySukFXFohiUmAdPUVH8NCoQ" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Beaded viking longboat</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>religion</category>
  <category>catholic</category>
  <category>lent</category>
  <guid>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/capernaum.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://images-wixmp-ed30a86b8c4ca887773594c2.wixmp.com/f/f94db2db-b96a-432a-94d7-028d717c10a1/d6w1mnf-bb72cc4a-3fa3-4f0f-b48b-61dc7a273f0a.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_498,q_70,strp/beaded_viking_longboat_by_anabiyeni_d6w1mnf-375w-2x.jpg?token=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJzdWIiOiJ1cm46YXBwOjdlMGQxODg5ODIyNjQzNzNhNWYwZDQxNWVhMGQyNmUwIiwiaXNzIjoidXJuOmFwcDo3ZTBkMTg4OTgyMjY0MzczYTVmMGQ0MTVlYTBkMjZlMCIsIm9iaiI6W1t7ImhlaWdodCI6Ijw9NDk4IiwicGF0aCI6IlwvZlwvZjk0ZGIyZGItYjk2YS00MzJhLTk0ZDctMDI4ZDcxN2MxMGExXC9kNncxbW5mLWJiNzJjYzRhLTNmYTMtNGYwZi1iNDhiLTYxZGM3YTI3M2YwYS5qcGciLCJ3aWR0aCI6Ijw9NjAwIn1dXSwiYXVkIjpbInVybjpzZXJ2aWNlOmltYWdlLm9wZXJhdGlvbnMiXX0.5Mf-X2W32ArKdnjsxHWOySukFXFohiUmAdPUVH8NCoQ" medium="image"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Jesus calls the fishermen</title>
  <dc:creator>Abby Stamm</dc:creator>
  <link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/zebedee.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The week of my dad’s birthday is always hard for me. I miss his support and advice. I miss the way he would listen to whatever I was struggling with, then without judgment, he’d ask, “What do you think?” When I was maybe ten he asked me, “Did God create humans or did humans create God?” I have been thinking about that question as I work through the Ignatian exercises.</p>
<p>My favorite activity this week was the reading from Matthew 4:18-22. This was another “Imagine yourself in the scene” activity. I imagined myself helping Zebedee mend his nets in the shore while his sons alternately mended nets and goofed off, as restless, dissatisfied boys are wont to do. The salty fishy smell was so strong I was struggling to breathe deeply and I kept hoping a breeze would pick up and offer reprieve from both the smell and the heat. Zebedee and I both noticed the itinerant preacher wandering past. A couple other fishermen, acquaintances of Zebedee’s sons, were wandering with him. I wondered who they had left manning their boat. Then the preacher called out to us. I stayed with Zebedee, not much interested in chasing after a bunch of young men; I’d done that enough as a teacher (please forgive the anachronism). Zebedee’s sons had no such reservations and with barely a “Farewell” to us, they were off.</p>
<p>The activity asked, “How do you feel about being included with those called to follow Jesus?” In the context of this reading, not good. I am not a young man and I don’t see myself in a group of young men. It isn’t lack of interest; I did the “how far will you go” thing with Peace Corps, and loved it. I’ve stood on the shores of Lake Victoria with people mending nets and I’ve hiked miles when no vehicle or bicycle taxi could be found. As much as I loved those days, I rarely miss them. I like my life now. In my imagination, I was content mending nets with Zebedee. Had I still been twenty-something and dreaming of Peace Corps, I might have run off with his sons instead, to be the token female in the group.</p>
<p>The image below is of a school of tiny fishes I made while living in Malawi. Read more about it on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/anabiyeni/art/Beaded-school-of-fishes-115200217">deviantArt</a>. Many of these fish were later regifted to random friends. Challenge: can you find the two Disney fish below?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://images-wixmp-ed30a86b8c4ca887773594c2.wixmp.com/f/f94db2db-b96a-432a-94d7-028d717c10a1/d1wl521-c02b7f45-c746-4a6b-b14e-2babb2dd533b.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_253,q_70,strp/beaded_school_of_fishes_by_anabiyeni_d1wl521-375w-2x.jpg?token=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJzdWIiOiJ1cm46YXBwOjdlMGQxODg5ODIyNjQzNzNhNWYwZDQxNWVhMGQyNmUwIiwiaXNzIjoidXJuOmFwcDo3ZTBkMTg4OTgyMjY0MzczYTVmMGQ0MTVlYTBkMjZlMCIsIm9iaiI6W1t7ImhlaWdodCI6Ijw9MjUzIiwicGF0aCI6IlwvZlwvZjk0ZGIyZGItYjk2YS00MzJhLTk0ZDctMDI4ZDcxN2MxMGExXC9kMXdsNTIxLWMwMmI3ZjQ1LWM3NDYtNGE2Yi1iMTRlLTJiYWJiMmRkNTMzYi5qcGciLCJ3aWR0aCI6Ijw9NjAwIn1dXSwiYXVkIjpbInVybjpzZXJ2aWNlOmltYWdlLm9wZXJhdGlvbnMiXX0.eJjVZpTmgeNq3YCVPSdUBe-KKxX8xn5rHqZX07Oxk0k" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Beaded school of fish</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>religion</category>
  <category>catholic</category>
  <category>lent</category>
  <guid>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/zebedee.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://images-wixmp-ed30a86b8c4ca887773594c2.wixmp.com/f/f94db2db-b96a-432a-94d7-028d717c10a1/d1wl521-c02b7f45-c746-4a6b-b14e-2babb2dd533b.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_253,q_70,strp/beaded_school_of_fishes_by_anabiyeni_d1wl521-375w-2x.jpg?token=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJzdWIiOiJ1cm46YXBwOjdlMGQxODg5ODIyNjQzNzNhNWYwZDQxNWVhMGQyNmUwIiwiaXNzIjoidXJuOmFwcDo3ZTBkMTg4OTgyMjY0MzczYTVmMGQ0MTVlYTBkMjZlMCIsIm9iaiI6W1t7ImhlaWdodCI6Ijw9MjUzIiwicGF0aCI6IlwvZlwvZjk0ZGIyZGItYjk2YS00MzJhLTk0ZDctMDI4ZDcxN2MxMGExXC9kMXdsNTIxLWMwMmI3ZjQ1LWM3NDYtNGE2Yi1iMTRlLTJiYWJiMmRkNTMzYi5qcGciLCJ3aWR0aCI6Ijw9NjAwIn1dXSwiYXVkIjpbInVybjpzZXJ2aWNlOmltYWdlLm9wZXJhdGlvbnMiXX0.eJjVZpTmgeNq3YCVPSdUBe-KKxX8xn5rHqZX07Oxk0k" medium="image"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Jesus is baptised</title>
  <dc:creator>Abby Stamm</dc:creator>
  <link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/patrick.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>We are in week two of the Ignatian lenten retreat. Today I’m going to focus on one of my reflections in week one, though. My favorite activities in the retreat are when we imagine ourselves in the scene. We can be anyone, Jesus, another named (or unnamed) character, or a random bystander. I most enjoy being a random bystander and thinking about, as myself (a self-insert?) I am there and what my reaction would be were I to experience whatever is happening.</p>
<p>My favorite activity in week one was on day four, when we were assigned to read Matthew 3:13-17 and instructed to imagine ourselves watching John the Baptist and Jesus. In my vision, I went to the riverbank to learn what John had to say. People had been talking about him and his teachings in my village and I was curious. I have no intention of being baptized, though; I’m terrified of water and whatever fauna may lurk beneath the surface.</p>
<p>While we are listening to John, his cousin shows up. We’ve seen him around; they seem to get on well and enjoy teasing each other. I am not there to listen to their banter, though. I tire quickly of their “Baptize me”, “No, you baptize me” and am thinking about leaving when John finally decides to humor his cousin. I’ll give him points for showmanship, though. He timed it for just as the sun is breaking through the clouds. If only I could figure out how he managed that creepy disembodied voice shouting about a beloved son.</p>
<p>I think my dissatisfaction with the Catholic church right now heavily colored my reading. I do enjoy the image of Jesus and John teasing each other like siblings, though. It makes them more three-dimensional for me, more relatable.</p>
<p>The image below is of a green striped zebra I made while living in Malawi. Read more about it on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/anabiyeni/art/Beaded-green-zebra-133388049">deviantArt</a>. I’m guessing it was the dry season and I was tired of the dusty brown everywhere.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://images-wixmp-ed30a86b8c4ca887773594c2.wixmp.com/f/f94db2db-b96a-432a-94d7-028d717c10a1/d27eyvl-173b7b55-c103-4411-93b0-522d52ca8106.jpg/v1/fit/w_678,h_525,q_70,strp/beaded_green_zebra_by_anabiyeni_d27eyvl-375w-2x.jpg?token=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJzdWIiOiJ1cm46YXBwOjdlMGQxODg5ODIyNjQzNzNhNWYwZDQxNWVhMGQyNmUwIiwiaXNzIjoidXJuOmFwcDo3ZTBkMTg4OTgyMjY0MzczYTVmMGQ0MTVlYTBkMjZlMCIsIm9iaiI6W1t7ImhlaWdodCI6Ijw9NTI1IiwicGF0aCI6IlwvZlwvZjk0ZGIyZGItYjk2YS00MzJhLTk0ZDctMDI4ZDcxN2MxMGExXC9kMjdleXZsLTE3M2I3YjU1LWMxMDMtNDQxMS05M2IwLTUyMmQ1MmNhODEwNi5qcGciLCJ3aWR0aCI6Ijw9Njc4In1dXSwiYXVkIjpbInVybjpzZXJ2aWNlOmltYWdlLm9wZXJhdGlvbnMiXX0.WlBJlpYG2KxSh2m7EtyW4IWQs1It-uK5HodvAb-KoM4" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Beaded green and white zebra sculpture</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>religion</category>
  <category>lent</category>
  <category>catholic</category>
  <guid>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/patrick.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://images-wixmp-ed30a86b8c4ca887773594c2.wixmp.com/f/f94db2db-b96a-432a-94d7-028d717c10a1/d27eyvl-173b7b55-c103-4411-93b0-522d52ca8106.jpg/v1/fit/w_678,h_525,q_70,strp/beaded_green_zebra_by_anabiyeni_d27eyvl-375w-2x.jpg?token=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJzdWIiOiJ1cm46YXBwOjdlMGQxODg5ODIyNjQzNzNhNWYwZDQxNWVhMGQyNmUwIiwiaXNzIjoidXJuOmFwcDo3ZTBkMTg4OTgyMjY0MzczYTVmMGQ0MTVlYTBkMjZlMCIsIm9iaiI6W1t7ImhlaWdodCI6Ijw9NTI1IiwicGF0aCI6IlwvZlwvZjk0ZGIyZGItYjk2YS00MzJhLTk0ZDctMDI4ZDcxN2MxMGExXC9kMjdleXZsLTE3M2I3YjU1LWMxMDMtNDQxMS05M2IwLTUyMmQ1MmNhODEwNi5qcGciLCJ3aWR0aCI6Ijw9Njc4In1dXSwiYXVkIjpbInVybjpzZXJ2aWNlOmltYWdlLm9wZXJhdGlvbnMiXX0.WlBJlpYG2KxSh2m7EtyW4IWQs1It-uK5HodvAb-KoM4" medium="image"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lenten activities</title>
  <dc:creator>Abby Stamm</dc:creator>
  <link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/ignatius/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I was raised in and east-coast Roman Catholic university community. Since leaving that small progressive enclave, I’ve struggled to find a Catholic church where I feel welcome to be myself, or in some cases welcome at all. Here in the twin cities, I stopped trying. Now I attend an Episcopal church near my house. I have found them to be welcoming and supportive as I discern who I am and what I believe. Best of all, there is no expectation that I convert to Episcopalianism.</p>
<p>There is a Jesuit church near my house that organizes Lenten Ignatian retreats. Since I was raised to believe strongly in social justice and in discernment, which are both important in Ignatian theology, I signed up to participate. The group has only met once so far and I did not know anyone in advance, so I am curious what I will learn.</p>
<p>Last year I had participated in a Lenten group led by the priest. By the end of Lent, the group was just the priest and me, which felt awkward mostly because the priest actively disagreed with half of what I said and failed to understand most of the rest. The point of the retreats is to learn together and build on each other’s observations, not shut people down by invalidating them.</p>
<p>The image below is of an angel I made over 15 years ago. I was living in Malawi at the time and had not brought a nativity set with me, so I made one. You can find the rest of the set on <a href="https://deviantart.com/anabiyeni">deviantArt</a>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://images-wixmp-ed30a86b8c4ca887773594c2.wixmp.com/f/f94db2db-b96a-432a-94d7-028d717c10a1/d1wow7b-ce384790-5b2a-46c5-b03f-be42b664d554.jpg/v1/fill/w_845,h_946,q_70,strp/beaded_nativity_angel_by_anabiyeni_d1wow7b-pre.jpg?token=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJzdWIiOiJ1cm46YXBwOjdlMGQxODg5ODIyNjQzNzNhNWYwZDQxNWVhMGQyNmUwIiwiaXNzIjoidXJuOmFwcDo3ZTBkMTg4OTgyMjY0MzczYTVmMGQ0MTVlYTBkMjZlMCIsIm9iaiI6W1t7ImhlaWdodCI6Ijw9OTg0IiwicGF0aCI6IlwvZlwvZjk0ZGIyZGItYjk2YS00MzJhLTk0ZDctMDI4ZDcxN2MxMGExXC9kMXdvdzdiLWNlMzg0NzkwLTViMmEtNDZjNS1iMDNmLWJlNDJiNjY0ZDU1NC5qcGciLCJ3aWR0aCI6Ijw9ODc5In1dXSwiYXVkIjpbInVybjpzZXJ2aWNlOmltYWdlLm9wZXJhdGlvbnMiXX0.e8d8ZfqnOUq2GhbHcFyw2wS0qb9qt2e4JIB9YRNVmlc" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Beaded white angel doll</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>religion</category>
  <category>catholic</category>
  <category>lent</category>
  <guid>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/ignatius/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://images-wixmp-ed30a86b8c4ca887773594c2.wixmp.com/f/f94db2db-b96a-432a-94d7-028d717c10a1/d1wow7b-ce384790-5b2a-46c5-b03f-be42b664d554.jpg/v1/fill/w_845,h_946,q_70,strp/beaded_nativity_angel_by_anabiyeni_d1wow7b-pre.jpg?token=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJzdWIiOiJ1cm46YXBwOjdlMGQxODg5ODIyNjQzNzNhNWYwZDQxNWVhMGQyNmUwIiwiaXNzIjoidXJuOmFwcDo3ZTBkMTg4OTgyMjY0MzczYTVmMGQ0MTVlYTBkMjZlMCIsIm9iaiI6W1t7ImhlaWdodCI6Ijw9OTg0IiwicGF0aCI6IlwvZlwvZjk0ZGIyZGItYjk2YS00MzJhLTk0ZDctMDI4ZDcxN2MxMGExXC9kMXdvdzdiLWNlMzg0NzkwLTViMmEtNDZjNS1iMDNmLWJlNDJiNjY0ZDU1NC5qcGciLCJ3aWR0aCI6Ijw9ODc5In1dXSwiYXVkIjpbInVybjpzZXJ2aWNlOmltYWdlLm9wZXJhdGlvbnMiXX0.e8d8ZfqnOUq2GhbHcFyw2wS0qb9qt2e4JIB9YRNVmlc" medium="image"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Welcome To My Blog</title>
  <dc:creator>Abby Stamm</dc:creator>
  <link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/welcome/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I work at the state department of health. While I was trained as a health educator and epidemiologist, I do neither of those right now. I may write later about some of the work I am doing.</p>
<p>In this blog, I plan to focus on activities outside of work, such as my art, Toastmasters, and church activities. I may also write about local events and activities with family and friends.</p>
<p>The image below is of an HIV virus I made 10 years ago, when I believed after graduation I would find another job in HIV work. (Spoiler: I did not.)</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://images-wixmp-ed30a86b8c4ca887773594c2.wixmp.com/f/f94db2db-b96a-432a-94d7-028d717c10a1/d8hytr4-02e87ec5-cc92-49ae-b156-dc43959b3c45.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_569,q_70,strp/beaded_hiv_virus_by_anabiyeni_d8hytr4-375w-2x.jpg?token=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJzdWIiOiJ1cm46YXBwOjdlMGQxODg5ODIyNjQzNzNhNWYwZDQxNWVhMGQyNmUwIiwiaXNzIjoidXJuOmFwcDo3ZTBkMTg4OTgyMjY0MzczYTVmMGQ0MTVlYTBkMjZlMCIsIm9iaiI6W1t7ImhlaWdodCI6Ijw9NTY5IiwicGF0aCI6IlwvZlwvZjk0ZGIyZGItYjk2YS00MzJhLTk0ZDctMDI4ZDcxN2MxMGExXC9kOGh5dHI0LTAyZTg3ZWM1LWNjOTItNDlhZS1iMTU2LWRjNDM5NTliM2M0NS5qcGciLCJ3aWR0aCI6Ijw9NjAwIn1dXSwiYXVkIjpbInVybjpzZXJ2aWNlOmltYWdlLm9wZXJhdGlvbnMiXX0.fJumuJbPyItodXvCz7rX5ynNuA5bFGKo4IOgyeyQQs8" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Beaded orange sculpture of an HIV virus</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/welcome/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://images-wixmp-ed30a86b8c4ca887773594c2.wixmp.com/f/f94db2db-b96a-432a-94d7-028d717c10a1/d8hytr4-02e87ec5-cc92-49ae-b156-dc43959b3c45.jpg/v1/fit/w_600,h_569,q_70,strp/beaded_hiv_virus_by_anabiyeni_d8hytr4-375w-2x.jpg?token=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJzdWIiOiJ1cm46YXBwOjdlMGQxODg5ODIyNjQzNzNhNWYwZDQxNWVhMGQyNmUwIiwiaXNzIjoidXJuOmFwcDo3ZTBkMTg4OTgyMjY0MzczYTVmMGQ0MTVlYTBkMjZlMCIsIm9iaiI6W1t7ImhlaWdodCI6Ijw9NTY5IiwicGF0aCI6IlwvZlwvZjk0ZGIyZGItYjk2YS00MzJhLTk0ZDctMDI4ZDcxN2MxMGExXC9kOGh5dHI0LTAyZTg3ZWM1LWNjOTItNDlhZS1iMTU2LWRjNDM5NTliM2M0NS5qcGciLCJ3aWR0aCI6Ijw9NjAwIn1dXSwiYXVkIjpbInVybjpzZXJ2aWNlOmltYWdlLm9wZXJhdGlvbnMiXX0.fJumuJbPyItodXvCz7rX5ynNuA5bFGKo4IOgyeyQQs8" medium="image"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
