<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Where the branches meet the roots</title>
<link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/blog.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<image>
<url>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/images/water-tree-root-mosaic.png</url>
<title>Where the branches meet the roots</title>
<link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/blog.html</link>
<height>13</height>
<width>144</width>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.5.57</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 04:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Crown of thorns</title>
  <dc:creator>Abby Stamm</dc:creator>
  <link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/thorns.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Human Resources (HR) at work has decided to rescind the at-risk letters, properly evaluate who they can afford to lose across the department of health, and resend layoff letters on Easter Monday. For better or worse, at least they are following the union contract now. The language in the union contract is outdated and does ot apply to the reality at work. It stipulated that people whose jobs are being terminated can steal jobs from people with the same job classification, but lower seniority. The problem is “Research scientist” can mean bench scientist, informatician, data manager, epidemiologist, data analyst, and computer programmer. Most people are not more than two or three of those things, but in theory, as the contract is written, an epidemiologist who has never worked in a lab could steal the job of a bench scientist. HR decide entirely on their own based only on minimum qualifications, with no input from relevant supervisors.</p>
<p>We all anticipate any job stealing will go badly and lead to even more chaos than that introduced first by the botched at-risk letters, then in the next few weeks by the mass layoffs (not to mention the 120 people who have already been laid off and whose work halted overnight). I’m feeling especially jaded as I try to continue the Lenten readings.</p>
<p>My reading today was from Matthew 27:27-31. This was another “Imagine yourself in the scene” activity. I am watching, perhaps as a Roman soldier, or a slave, someone without power or agency of my own. Other soldiers drag Jesus into the room, strip him, and dress him in a military tunic. I think as a revolutionary and a threat to Roman rule, they see him as a soldier, anyway. The crown and reed feel over the top and tell me far more about them and their fears and insecurities than they do about Jesus, who refuses to respond to their bullying. Then, bullying unsuccessful and victim unprovoked, they claim back the tunic and return his clothes.</p>
<p>The discussion questions fall flat for me.</p>
<p>Question 1: Could I endure pain without complaint? Given the way I spoke out after I was sexually assaulted, I’m guessing not, and that’s fine with me. Silent suffering does no one any good.</p>
<p>Question 2: Could I ignore ignorant criticism? It depends. I often wear a headscarf and have been coded as Muslim both by people who greet me with an excited “Salaam aleichum” and by people who actively shun me or say things like “Go back to your own country.” I see no point in telling the latter I was born in Wisconsin, so I ignore them. I also ignore the people who see my Pride accessories and tell me I’m going to hell. Much like the soldiers, their behavior toward me tells me they are insecure, perhaps afraid, and I pity them.</p>
<p>Question 3: What do I want Jesus to tell me as he suffers? Nothing. I want Jesus to focus on whatever he needs to focus on and the random soldier/slave/bystander I happen to represent is irrelevant. I wonder at the arrogance that must be necessary for someone to expect to be the primary focus of anyone in pain. Where is their compassion?</p>
<p>At work, we are all suffering through the uncertainty and anxiety together. We are all trying to support each other and give each other grace even as we suffer ourselves. Then someone from HR will say, in effect, “Look at me! I’m sorry for the anxiety you feel, but not really, because it’s all about me! Don’t you feel sorry for me?” And we are all just staring at the latest email full of platitudes, or listening to the latest HR meeting (no chat, no Q&amp;A, no way for us to interact) full of more platitudes and think, “Feel sorry for you? When you won’t give us any straight answers and deliberately keep us uninformed? Are you mad?” I do not want to be like HR, ever. If someone is suffering, my focus should be on them, not me. Even if I am suffering, if they are, too, I would never want to expect their support, and if they offer it anyway, I should feel honored, not entitled.</p>
<p>The image below is of two beaded camels wearing bridles and saddles. Read more about it on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/anabiyeni/art/Beaded-costumed-camels-150233540">deviantArt</a>. I have very few beaded soldiers (Starfleet officers, a Romulan commander, and a knight from the show Merlin) and none of them are from Jesus’ time, so instead you get a a couple fancy camels that might have been part of Herod’s procession.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/images/beaded_camels.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Beaded bedecked camels</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>religion</category>
  <category>catholic</category>
  <category>lent</category>
  <guid>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/thorns.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/images/beaded_camels.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Watching in the garden</title>
  <dc:creator>Abby Stamm</dc:creator>
  <link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/gethsemane.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>My reading for today was from Matthew 26:30-46. This was another “Imagine yourself in the scene” activity I chose it today because it’s the first reading of Week 6. I’ve followed Jesus and his best friends to Gethsemane. I’m not sure why I’m here. I feel a bit like I’m encroaching on private friends’ time and maybe I should leave. I suppose my curiosity is overcoming my sense of propriety.</p>
<p>Jesus asks his friends to keep watch before going to pray. They fall asleep, which means they don’t notice me and chase me away. Jesus sounds upset, like every revolutionary ever. He has a mission that frustrates and angers and exhausts him, but he feels too strongly about it, identifies too strongly with it, to quit, despite the inherent dangers of being a revolutionary. So he’s having an especially bad day, which makes sense if someone tipped him off that he’ll be arrested today. Apparently it wasn’t his best friends; I can’t imagine they’d fall asleep if they expect he will be arrested today.</p>
<p>And three’s the charm. After Jesus’ third prayer, he concludes, I suppose, that it’s best to stop hiding in the garden and get on with whatever is going to happen next. I stay hidden while they leave the garden. His friends look groggy, confused, maybe frustrated by his endless riddles. Better them than me; I’m bad at riddles and worse at subtlety.</p>
<p>I feel sorry for Jesus, and for every other revolutionary who prays for a better world for everyone, especially the most marginalized, when they are doubting themselves. I feel far sorrier for those doing the marginalizing, that they are so out of touch with the world, maybe due to unhealed trauma, past pain or loss, or some other thing that hinders their self-awareness and awareness of the pain they cause others.</p>
<p>I struggle with being aware of others and of my effect on them. However, if someone points out how I hurt them or someone else, I contemplate their words. Then I make an effort to mitigate the harm. Often this means minding my words in the future, maybe an apology in the moment, something easy to do and easy to remember. I wish my country’s leaders would do at least that much.</p>
<p>The image below is of two horses from the Danish card game, Bella Sara. Paris is the armored horse on the left. Wildflower, the pony on the right, has flowers in her mane and tail. This pair feels appropriate for a Gethsemane scene. Read more about this pair on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/anabiyeni/art/Beaded-Bella-Sara-Paris-and-Wildflower-879625927">deviantArt</a>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/images/beaded_paris_wildflower.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>beaded horses Paris and Wildflower</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>religion</category>
  <category>catholic</category>
  <category>lent</category>
  <category>work</category>
  <guid>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/gethsemane.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/images/beaded_paris_wildflower.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Vineyard tenants</title>
  <dc:creator>Abby Stamm</dc:creator>
  <link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/vintner.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>We are in week six of the Ignatian Lenten retreat, but I didn’t participate at all last week with everything at work, so now I’m playing catch-up. Work has been a mixture of putting projects on hold until we know how many people on our team will be laid off and preparing for our presentation yesterday at <em>ShinyConf</em>.</p>
<p>The presentation went well and now Eric wants to create an R package that simplifies making online dashboards accessible. This afternoon, we discussed what such a package would look like. I think it will be a mix of accessibility checks and functions to simplify adding accessible content. Functions would cover things like alt text, aria labels, and maybe a color suggester like my coworker’s <a href="https://aboricholololo.shinyapps.io/ColorOptimizer/">Color Optimizer</a>. I suggested we should have a function generate a report called the Accessibility Audit.</p>
<p>My prayer activity today is a reading from Luke 20:9-19. I don’t understand this parable, so I struggled a bit. I am watching from a distance. Perhaps I am in the next vineyard, or a relative of a tenant in this one. I don’t understand what the tenants are thinking by refusing to pay. Do they want to be thrown out? Then to attack the man’s slaves, who have less freedom than they? Are they bullies? I don’t have a clue what they expect to accomplish. What’s their cause? Why are they willing to risk being evicted? I don’t understand the landlord, either. Should he not have evicted them after the third strike? I feel sorry for his son, a naive young man who has never struggled a day in his life. I am not surprised they don’t heed him. I am surprised they kill him. To what end? Do they think they will be able to steal the land? The landlord’s status is higher than theirs and they’ve killed his son now; he has the might of the local law enforcement behind him. So he kills and replaces them. That’s predictable, at least.</p>
<p>According to my annotated bible, the vineyard is Israel and the landlord’s son is Jesus, but I don’t get it. Jesus wasn’t a naive heir; he was a threat to the Romans. And Israel as the vineyard I also don’t follow, unless Jesus was hoping the Romans would be wiped out, which is possible. I chose this reading today because I’ve been thinking about work and bullies and misuse of power.</p>
<p>At work we still have no idea who or how many people will be laid off in two weeks, which positions will be entirely eliminated, which teams might be entirely disbanded or absorbed into other teams, how layoffs were selected. People I’ve spoken to understand there’s no money and people need to be laid off, but the entire process has been chaotic and opaque, with no meaningful attempt to calm or reassure us. The empty platitudes we have received are worse than useless - they breed resentment.</p>
<p>Much as I don’t understand the tenants in this parable who ultimately and shortsightedly destroyed themselves, I don’t understand the entirely unnecessary and drawn-out trauma our leadership is inflicting on the Department of Health. It’s leading to distrust in leadership, burnout, fear, and fatigue among very talented, very hard-working staff, many of whom are veterans of COVID (myself included), who are now asking if maybe they should be looking for jobs elsewhere even if they did not get at-risk letters. The public health system here, and throughout the US, is suffering from insufficient capacity and cannot afford to lose any more good workers, so why is my department’s leadership trying to drive people away on top of the layoffs? I feel like one of the landlord’s slaves, unheard and unvalued.</p>
<p>The image below is of a Malawian oxcart pulled by two European oxen. I made the oxcart and a couple zebus to pull it while serving in the Peace Corps. Seven years later, I finally photographed it, but I’d managed to lose the zebus in the interim. Read more about this set on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/anabiyeni/art/Beaded-African-ox-cart-115200840">deviantArt</a>. I chose this image because the slaves had no agency and no idea what they were walking into, much like the cattle here.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/images/beaded_oxcart.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Beaded oxcart pulled by two oxen</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>religion</category>
  <category>lent</category>
  <category>catholic</category>
  <guid>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/vintner.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/images/beaded_oxcart.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Judas’ betrayal</title>
  <dc:creator>Abby Stamm</dc:creator>
  <link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/judas.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>My reading for today was from Mark 14:43-52. This was an “Imagine yourself in the scene” activity from last year’s retreat. I chose it today because I’ve been thinking about it all week. Two wees ago, a few friends were laid off from work overnight - called in the evening and told not to show up for work the next day, and by the way, their accounts were already deactivated with no chance to hand over any of their outstanding work. Last week, more friends received emails about midday informing them that they had been laid off and they had half an hour for handover before their accounts would be deactivated. Still more friends will not know their fate until next week.</p>
<p>I work for the state department of health. These layoffs immediately followed the federal government’s decision to withhold “COVID” funds, citing nonsense about the COVID pandemic being over. First, the COVID pandemic is not over. Second, those funds were not just being used for COVID. They were funding desperately needed data infrastructure and disease surveillance improvements. Surveillance that included monitoring outbreaks of Measles, Bird Flu, and other infectious diseases.</p>
<p>In Minnesota, from what I understand, the two divisions most impacted by the loss of those funds were the infectious disease division and the data strategy and interoperability office, where I work. The loss of so many staff in these divisions has already started to adversely impact the work of local public health, tribal health, and the residents of Minnesota. We can only guess what the long-term impact will be as we struggle to stabilize existing infrastructure and maintain relationships.</p>
<p>I chose this reading, of Judas betraying Jesus, because I feel much like I imagine Jesus feels here, betrayed by someone he trusted and trying to remain calm and keep his followers calm. We have been betrayed by the federal government. We feel angry, but violence is not the answer. Like Jesus, we are watching decades of public health work crumble, hastened along by people wo do not value public health, who do not care about the marginalized, the very people Jesus and the prophets before him preached to protect. The federal government is trying to erase data on women, people of color, members of the LGBTQ+ community, people with disabilities, and those experiencing environmental injustice, in short anyone who is not a rich white cisgender male. Jesus was not rich or white and 2000 years ago, the concept of cisgender did not exist.</p>
<p>In some apocryphal stories, Judas repented. I pray that the leaders of this country, like Judas, will one day realize and understand the harm they have caused. In the meantime, I pray that those of us left in public health can find ways to continue our work to protect and preserve the health of the people in our communities, especially those who are most marginalized.</p>
<p>The image below is of the cat I had in Uganda, Enshonga the terror, attacking the horse stable I had worked so hard to make. My goal that night was to take a photograph of my art to send home to my parents, but Enshonga had other ideas. Her wanton disregard for the hard work I put into my art fits the mood at work right now. Read more about this piece on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/anabiyeni/art/My-cat-attacked-my-stable-181609113">deviantArt</a>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/images/beaded_enshonga_stable.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>pet cat attacks beaded horse stable</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>religion</category>
  <category>catholic</category>
  <category>lent</category>
  <category>work</category>
  <guid>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/judas.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/images/beaded_enshonga_stable.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Sermon on the mountain</title>
  <dc:creator>Abby Stamm</dc:creator>
  <link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/tiberias.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This week has been difficult at work. Decisions from higher-ups have left me feeling bewildered, uncertain, and unvalued. My interpretation of the reading I chose for today reflected that.</p>
<p>My second reading this week was from John 6:1-14. This was another “Imagine yourself in the scene” activity. I imagined myself curious as I wandered after the crowd that was following Jesus. Some grasped his robes, begging for healing. Others pushed their children into his arms, seeking blessings. Some watched him warily. Many, like me, were just curious. His fame preceded him and we wanted to know if he was as great as the tales would have us believe. By the time we reached the field on the mountain - perhaps a shelf or plateau or saddle - most of the women and children had dropped away, leaving only men and a few older boys and me.</p>
<p>One of the boys carried a basket of bread and salted fish, probably diverted on his way home from the market. When Jesus declared the people (read: men) must be fed, the disciples commandeered his basket. Then they passed out the food to the men, who must have been ashamed seeing the boy lose his entire basket, because they coughed up whatever they were carrying stone soup style so in the end, everyone had food. I hoped someone would remember to return the boy’s basket with food for his family, but with his usefulness ended, the disciples apparently forgot entirely that he existed. I have felt a lot like that boy this week.</p>
<p>The activity asked, “In what way are you hungry?” I’m seeking a spiritual community that embodies the phrase “All are welcome” without shame or fear or discrimination or erasure, a community that meets people where they are and accepts them for who they are, even when the members don’t understand them. My favorite line in the Nicene Creed is “We believe in one holy catholic apostolic church”. That is the community I want, where what and how you believe don’t matter nearly as much as being part of the community and supporting and being supported by the community.</p>
<p>The image below is of a beaded flying dragon-type serpent called an amphiptere. Read more about it on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/anabiyeni/art/Beaded-pastel-amphiptere-118679559">deviantArt</a>. I wanted to pick an art piece more relevant to the story, but I’ve never made beaded bread and apparently I never posted my beaded basket online. Mountain made me think dragon, so here we are. Also, it’s spring (for a few days, until we get more snow) here in Minnesota, so pastel feels appropriate.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/images/beaded_pastel_dragon.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Beaded flying serpent</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>religion</category>
  <category>catholic</category>
  <category>lent</category>
  <guid>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/tiberias.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/images/beaded_pastel_dragon.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Wedding at Cana</title>
  <dc:creator>Abby Stamm</dc:creator>
  <link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/cana.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>My favorite activity this week was the reading from John 2:1-12. This was another “Imagine yourself in the scene” activity. I imagined myself gossiping with the agogos (grandmothers) and some other women, including Mary and the mother of the groom. We watch the other guests, the newly married couple, Mary’s son with his friends. I wonder how they were invited, but feel it would be rude to ask. Maybe they are friends of the groom.</p>
<p>At some point, a nervous steward comes over to tell the mother of the groom that the wine is nearly finished. Personally, I feel there has been enough drinking today, but many of the guests, that rowdy group with Jesus for example, will not respond well if the wine runs out. Mary, the enabler, calls her son over to enlist his help. A few of us speculate how far he will travel and how much he will pay to find sufficient wine to last this crowd through the night. I had expected he would be all for dragging off a few friends to find more wine and be the heroes of the moment, so I am surprised by his rude response. Then I recall how rowdy some of his friends and wonder if he feels as I do, that there has been quite enough drinking tonight. Nonetheless, he acquiesces and leaves to do her bidding.</p>
<p>A short time later, the steward reappears with wine I am informed is high quality and we again start speculating about the cost. He won’t say where the wine had come from, but some of the other workers claim Jesus had created it, somehow magicked water into wine like witchcraft. I decide it’s probably best to stay quiet. While I don’t condemn witchcraft out of hand, I am wary of it until I know the caster’s intentions. Most of the rest of the guests are just happy there’s more wine and think nothing of it until the story starts to spread the next day and they are quick to point out, “We were there!” I stay quiet and watch.</p>
<p>The activity asked, “How do you respond to Jesus turning water into wine?” Wary. That stunt served no purpose except maybe to irk his mother, who was concerned only for her friend’s reputation. Why was he so annoyed with her anyway? Because he knew her request was selfish? I don’t understand how this is a noteworthy miracle.</p>
<p>The image below is of a wine charm I made years ago. Read more about it on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/anabiyeni/art/Beaded-grape-wine-charm-133452420">deviantArt</a>. Around that time, my mother had complained we didn’t have enough wine charms for all of the guests at our winter solstice parties, where we’d serve glog made from dad’s homemade wine, so I made several wine charms from old necklace pendants and bracelet charms. This is one of maybe a dozen that I made out of beads, and one of the few that I have kept. I recall the wine glass had been part of a gift box of Harlequin romances. I kept the glass because I liked the color; I never got around to reading the books.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/images/beaded_grape.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Wine glass with wine charm of beaded grapes</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>religion</category>
  <category>catholic</category>
  <category>lent</category>
  <guid>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/cana.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/images/beaded_grape.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Boat to Capernaum</title>
  <dc:creator>Abby Stamm</dc:creator>
  <link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/capernaum.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This week also saw a reading from John 6:16-21. This was another “Imagine yourself in the scene” activity. I get motion sick very easily. I found myself reliving crossing Lake Malawi in a dhow during the rainy season. Some distance from shore, visibility dropped to zero, so the crew stopped the boat in the middle of the lake and waited for the storm to calm. I stayed by the back, drenched through, retching, and struggling just to breathe. The crew and most of my friends huddled under the tarp in the middle of the boat, but crew members were smoking there and I wanted to avoid smoke-induced nausea on top of sesickness.</p>
<p>I imagined the disciples’ crossing was much like my own journey had been. Placing myself in the scene, I was just as seasick as I’d been on Lake Malawi. As a result, if I noticed Jesus at all, I shrugged him off as a hallucination. Likely I did not notice him and was only vaguely aware of the disciples shouting. I probably assumed they were shouting at each other about the storm. They knew how sick I was; they’d likely leave me be until we reached shore.</p>
<p>The activity asked, “How do you feel when you realize you are on the shore?” I was grateful the seasickness passed quickly and I could finally focus on something other than my stomach and esophagus. Of course, by that time Jesus was long gone. Hearing the crew retell it - “How did you miss it?” they asked me - I thought they must have hallucinated. Then I went in search of beer (being generally safer to drink than water) to wash the bile out of my mouth.</p>
<p>The image below is of a Viking longboat made of Delica beads. Read more about it on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/anabiyeni/art/Beaded-Viking-Longboat-416620779">deviantArt</a>. I made it about 15 years after I spent a semester in Denmark studying Nordic culture and history.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/images/beaded_;ongboat.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Beaded viking longboat</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>religion</category>
  <category>catholic</category>
  <category>lent</category>
  <guid>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/capernaum.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/images/beaded_longboat.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Jesus calls the fishermen</title>
  <dc:creator>Abby Stamm</dc:creator>
  <link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/zebedee.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The week of my dad’s birthday is always hard for me. I miss his support and advice. I miss the way he would listen to whatever I was struggling with, then without judgment, he’d ask, “What do you think?” When I was maybe ten he asked me, “Did God create humans or did humans create God?” I have been thinking about that question as I work through the Ignatian exercises.</p>
<p>My favorite activity this week was the reading from Matthew 4:18-22. This was another “Imagine yourself in the scene” activity. I imagined myself helping Zebedee mend his nets in the shore while his sons alternately mended nets and goofed off, as restless, dissatisfied boys are wont to do. The salty fishy smell was so strong I was struggling to breathe deeply and I kept hoping a breeze would pick up and offer reprieve from both the smell and the heat. Zebedee and I both noticed the itinerant preacher wandering past. A couple other fishermen, acquaintances of Zebedee’s sons, were wandering with him. I wondered who they had left manning their boat. Then the preacher called out to us. I stayed with Zebedee, not much interested in chasing after a bunch of young men; I’d done that enough as a teacher (please forgive the anachronism). Zebedee’s sons had no such reservations and with barely a “Farewell” to us, they were off.</p>
<p>The activity asked, “How do you feel about being included with those called to follow Jesus?” In the context of this reading, not good. I am not a young man and I don’t see myself in a group of young men. It isn’t lack of interest; I did the “how far will you go” thing with Peace Corps, and loved it. I’ve stood on the shores of Lake Victoria with people mending nets and I’ve hiked miles when no vehicle or bicycle taxi could be found. As much as I loved those days, I rarely miss them. I like my life now. In my imagination, I was content mending nets with Zebedee. Had I still been twenty-something and dreaming of Peace Corps, I might have run off with his sons instead, to be the token female in the group.</p>
<p>The image below is of a school of tiny fishes I made while living in Malawi. Read more about it on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/anabiyeni/art/Beaded-school-of-fishes-115200217">deviantArt</a>. Many of these fish were later regifted to random friends. Challenge: can you find the two Disney fish below?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/images/beaded_fishes.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Beaded school of fish</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>religion</category>
  <category>catholic</category>
  <category>lent</category>
  <guid>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/zebedee.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/images/beaded_fishes.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Jesus is baptised</title>
  <dc:creator>Abby Stamm</dc:creator>
  <link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/patrick.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>We are in week two of the Ignatian lenten retreat. Today I’m going to focus on one of my reflections in week one, though. My favorite activities in the retreat are when we imagine ourselves in the scene. We can be anyone, Jesus, another named (or unnamed) character, or a random bystander. I most enjoy being a random bystander and thinking about, as myself (a self-insert?) I am there and what my reaction would be were I to experience whatever is happening.</p>
<p>My favorite activity in week one was on day four, when we were assigned to read Matthew 3:13-17 and instructed to imagine ourselves watching John the Baptist and Jesus. In my vision, I went to the riverbank to learn what John had to say. People had been talking about him and his teachings in my village and I was curious. I have no intention of being baptized, though; I’m terrified of water and whatever fauna may lurk beneath the surface.</p>
<p>While we are listening to John, his cousin shows up. We’ve seen him around; they seem to get on well and enjoy teasing each other. I am not there to listen to their banter, though. I tire quickly of their “Baptize me”, “No, you baptize me” and am thinking about leaving when John finally decides to humor his cousin. I’ll give him points for showmanship, though. He timed it for just as the sun is breaking through the clouds. If only I could figure out how he managed that creepy disembodied voice shouting about a beloved son.</p>
<p>I think my dissatisfaction with the Catholic church right now heavily colored my reading. I do enjoy the image of Jesus and John teasing each other like siblings, though. It makes them more three-dimensional for me, more relatable.</p>
<p>The image below is of a green striped zebra I made while living in Malawi. Read more about it on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/anabiyeni/art/Beaded-green-zebra-133388049">deviantArt</a>. I’m guessing it was the dry season and I was tired of the dusty brown everywhere.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/images/beaded_green_zebra.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Beaded green and white zebra sculpture</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>religion</category>
  <category>lent</category>
  <category>catholic</category>
  <guid>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/patrick.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/lent_retreat_2025/images/beaded_green_zebra.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lenten activities</title>
  <dc:creator>Abby Stamm</dc:creator>
  <link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/ignatius/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I was raised in and east-coast Roman Catholic university community. Since leaving that small progressive enclave, I’ve struggled to find a Catholic church where I feel welcome to be myself, or in some cases welcome at all. Here in the twin cities, I stopped trying. Now I attend an Episcopal church near my house. I have found them to be welcoming and supportive as I discern who I am and what I believe. Best of all, there is no expectation that I convert to Episcopalianism.</p>
<p>There is a Jesuit church near my house that organizes Lenten Ignatian retreats. Since I was raised to believe strongly in social justice and in discernment, which are both important in Ignatian theology, I signed up to participate. The group has only met once so far and I did not know anyone in advance, so I am curious what I will learn.</p>
<p>Last year I had participated in a Lenten group led by the priest. By the end of Lent, the group was just the priest and me, which felt awkward mostly because the priest actively disagreed with half of what I said and failed to understand most of the rest. The point of the retreats is to learn together and build on each other’s observations, not shut people down by invalidating them.</p>
<p>The image below is of an angel I made over 15 years ago. Read more about it on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/anabiyeni/art/Beaded-nativity-angel-115375367">deviantArt</a>. I was living in Malawi at the time and had not brought a nativity set with me, so I made one.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/ignatius/beaded_angel.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Beaded white angel doll</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>religion</category>
  <category>catholic</category>
  <category>lent</category>
  <guid>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/ignatius/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/ignatius/beaded_angel.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Welcome To My Blog</title>
  <dc:creator>Abby Stamm</dc:creator>
  <link>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/welcome/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I work at the state department of health. While I was trained as a health educator and epidemiologist, I do neither of those right now. I may write later about some of the work I am doing.</p>
<p>I have wanted for years to start a blog, where I could write about whatever has most recently caught my attention. (My family has wanted me to start one ever since receiving my letters home from the Pace Corps twenty years ago.) I moved to Minnesota a little over a year ago to start a new job as an informatician and joined a religious community that is not the one in which I was raised. I have been making new friends and learning new things about myself and how I identify.</p>
<p>My goal with this blog is to write journal-type reflective pieces, maybe short stories about my daily experiences. I do not know yet how frequently I will update or what themes will emerge as I write. In this blog, I plan to focus on activities outside of work, such as my art, Toastmasters, and church activities. I may also write about local events and activities with family and friends.</p>
<p>The image below is of an HIV virus I made 10 years ago. Read more about it on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/anabiyeni/art/Beaded-HIV-virus-513907744">deviantArt</a>. Back then, I believed after graduation I would find another job in HIV work. (Spoiler: I did not.)</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/welcome/beaded_hiv.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Beaded orange sculpture of an HIV virus</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/welcome/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://ajstamm.github.io/musings/posts/welcome/beaded_hiv.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
